<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>MLRG</title><link href="https://complab-stonybrook.github.io/mlrg/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://complab-stonybrook.github.io/mlrg/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://complab-stonybrook.github.io/mlrg/</id><updated>2023-09-13T13:09:40-04:00</updated><entry><title>Automata for Tree TSL pt.1 (Sept 15)</title><link href="https://complab-stonybrook.github.io/mlrg/news/2023-fall/automata-for-tree-tsl-pt1-sept-15.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-09-13T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-09-13T13:09:40-04:00</updated><author><name>Logan Swanson</name></author><id>tag:complab-stonybrook.github.io,2023-09-13:/mlrg/news/2023-fall/automata-for-tree-tsl-pt1-sept-15.html</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Kenneth and Thomas will present an automata-theoretic perspective on TSL tree languages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fun has been promised.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="2023-Fall"></category></entry><entry><title>Philip on Identification in the Limit from Incomplete Positive Data (Sept 8)</title><link href="https://complab-stonybrook.github.io/mlrg/news/2023-fall/philip-on-identification-in-the-limit-from-incomplete-positive-data-sept-8.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-09-06T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-09-13T13:06:26-04:00</updated><author><name>Logan Swanson</name></author><id>tag:complab-stonybrook.github.io,2023-09-06:/mlrg/news/2023-fall/philip-on-identification-in-the-limit-from-incomplete-positive-data-sept-8.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is a practice talk for &lt;a href="https://www.uni-trier.de/en/universitaet/fachbereiche-faecher/fachbereich-iv/faecher/informatikwissenschaften/professuren/theoretische-informatik/research/conferences-and-workshops/fct-2023"&gt;FCT 2023&lt;/a&gt;, which will be given by Philip Kaelbling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Robust Identification in the Limit from Incomplete Positive Data
Philip Kaelbling, Dakotah Lambert, Jeffrey Heinz&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Intuitively, a learning algorithm is robust if it can succeed despite adverse conditions. We examine conditions under which learning algorithms …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is a practice talk for &lt;a href="https://www.uni-trier.de/en/universitaet/fachbereiche-faecher/fachbereich-iv/faecher/informatikwissenschaften/professuren/theoretische-informatik/research/conferences-and-workshops/fct-2023"&gt;FCT 2023&lt;/a&gt;, which will be given by Philip Kaelbling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Robust Identification in the Limit from Incomplete Positive Data
Philip Kaelbling, Dakotah Lambert, Jeffrey Heinz&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Intuitively, a learning algorithm is robust if it can succeed despite adverse conditions. We examine conditions under which learning algorithms for classes of formal languages are able to succeed when the data presentations are systematically incomplete; that is, when certain kinds of examples are systematically absent.  One motivation comes from linguistics, where the phonotactic pattern of a language may be understood as the intersection of formal languages, each of which formalizes a distinct linguistic generalization. We examine under what conditions these generalizations can be learned when the only data available to a learner belongs to their intersection.  In particular, we provide three formal definitions of robustness in the identification in the limit from positive data paradigm, and several theorems which describe the kinds of classes of formal languages which are, and are not, robustly learnable in the relevant sense. We relate these results to classes relevant to natural language phonology.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="2023-Fall"></category></entry><entry><title>First meeting September 1 at 1:15pm</title><link href="https://complab-stonybrook.github.io/mlrg/news/2023-fall/first-meeting-september-1-at-115pm.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-08-21T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-09-13T13:06:26-04:00</updated><author><name>Thomas Graf</name></author><id>tag:complab-stonybrook.github.io,2023-08-21:/mlrg/news/2023-fall/first-meeting-september-1-at-115pm.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Our &lt;em&gt;Mathematical Linguistics Re(ading|creation) Group&lt;/em&gt; (MLRG) will have its first meeting on the first Friday of the semester at 1:15pm:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Friday, September 1, 1:15-2:15pm&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will meet in the &lt;strong&gt;CompLab (SBS N-250)&lt;/strong&gt;.
We will finalize the time during that meeting, identify a student organizer for …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Our &lt;em&gt;Mathematical Linguistics Re(ading|creation) Group&lt;/em&gt; (MLRG) will have its first meeting on the first Friday of the semester at 1:15pm:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Friday, September 1, 1:15-2:15pm&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will meet in the &lt;strong&gt;CompLab (SBS N-250)&lt;/strong&gt;.
We will finalize the time during that meeting, identify a student organizer for this semester, and map out a rough schedule of presentations and activities. &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="2023-Fall"></category></entry><entry><title>Jordan on impact of corpus size at 1:30 pm (May 5)</title><link href="https://complab-stonybrook.github.io/mlrg/news/2023-spring/jordan-on-impact-of-corpus-size-at-130-pm-may-5.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-05-03T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-09-13T13:06:26-04:00</updated><author><name>Zhengxiang (Jack) Wang</name></author><id>tag:complab-stonybrook.github.io,2023-05-03:/mlrg/news/2023-spring/jordan-on-impact-of-corpus-size-at-130-pm-may-5.html</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I will discuss some recent findings on the impact of corpus size on the distribution of items in train-test splits for morphological inflection tasks. This can be tested empirically by taking many samples or calculated analytically. I will present and discuss some empirical results and an analytic solution. &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="2023-Spring"></category></entry><entry><title>Eric on authorship attribution at 1:30 pm (Apr 28)</title><link href="https://complab-stonybrook.github.io/mlrg/news/2023-spring/eric-on-authorship-attribution-at-130-pm-apr-28.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-04-24T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-09-13T13:06:26-04:00</updated><author><name>Zhengxiang (Jack) Wang</name></author><id>tag:complab-stonybrook.github.io,2023-04-24:/mlrg/news/2023-spring/eric-on-authorship-attribution-at-130-pm-apr-28.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;What defines an author’s writing style such that we can differentiate them from other authors? As humans, stylometric choices (i.e. the linguistic choice we make when writing) are innate, meaning we subconsciously make them without much thought. How can we build a system to automatically detect these stylistic …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;What defines an author’s writing style such that we can differentiate them from other authors? As humans, stylometric choices (i.e. the linguistic choice we make when writing) are innate, meaning we subconsciously make them without much thought. How can we build a system to automatically detect these stylistic choices in author’s documents, while also ignoring the content embedded within? Given a document, can we use these detected styles to automatically choose the correct author from a space of known authors? Additionally, we are concerned with &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; an author is chosen over the others, so explainability is an important factor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this talk, I will present my work on grammatical feature extraction and how we can generate grammatical “footprint” vectors. These vectors encapsulate author’s writing styles which can further be used for authorship identification, and later down the line, authorship obfuscation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="2023-Spring"></category></entry><entry><title>Thomas on subregular succinctness arguments at 1:30 pm (Apr 21)</title><link href="https://complab-stonybrook.github.io/mlrg/news/2023-spring/thomas-on-subregular-succinctness-arguments-at-130-pm-apr-21.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-04-18T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-09-13T13:06:26-04:00</updated><author><name>Zhengxiang (Jack) Wang</name></author><id>tag:complab-stonybrook.github.io,2023-04-18:/mlrg/news/2023-spring/thomas-on-subregular-succinctness-arguments-at-130-pm-apr-21.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Thomas will present a concrete case in syntax where subregular complexity considerations favor one of two competing analyses even though both have the same complexity. Concretely, both the Ban on Improper Movement and Stefan Keine's probe horizons are TSL over dependency trees, but they differ in succinctness. With probe horizons …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Thomas will present a concrete case in syntax where subregular complexity considerations favor one of two competing analyses even though both have the same complexity. Concretely, both the Ban on Improper Movement and Stefan Keine's probe horizons are TSL over dependency trees, but they differ in succinctness. With probe horizons, the number of tiers grows linearly with the number of features, whereas it grows quadratically in grammars with the Ban on Improper Movement. TSL succinctness thus favors probe horizons over the Ban on Improper Movement.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="2023-Spring"></category></entry><entry><title>Kenneth on island effects via pTSL for trees at 1:30 pm (Apr 14)</title><link href="https://complab-stonybrook.github.io/mlrg/news/2023-spring/kenneth-on-island-effects-via-ptsl-for-trees-at-130-pm-apr-14.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-04-12T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-09-13T13:06:26-04:00</updated><author><name>Zhengxiang (Jack) Wang</name></author><id>tag:complab-stonybrook.github.io,2023-04-12:/mlrg/news/2023-spring/kenneth-on-island-effects-via-ptsl-for-trees-at-130-pm-apr-14.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I will talk about a project me and Thomas contributed to using a probabilistic version of TSL* for trees, combining Thomas's tree TSL with Connor Mayer's string pTSL. We fit a model to experimental data on island effects from Sprouse et al 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;*TSL: Tier-based Strictly Local; pTSL: probabilistic TSL …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I will talk about a project me and Thomas contributed to using a probabilistic version of TSL* for trees, combining Thomas's tree TSL with Connor Mayer's string pTSL. We fit a model to experimental data on island effects from Sprouse et al 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;*TSL: Tier-based Strictly Local; pTSL: probabilistic TSL&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="2023-Spring"></category></entry><entry><title>Scott on rule interactions in phonology at 1:30 pm (Apr 7)</title><link href="https://complab-stonybrook.github.io/mlrg/news/2023-spring/scott-on-rule-interactions-in-phonology-at-130-pm-apr-7.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-04-04T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-09-13T13:06:26-04:00</updated><author><name>Zhengxiang (Jack) Wang</name></author><id>tag:complab-stonybrook.github.io,2023-04-04:/mlrg/news/2023-spring/scott-on-rule-interactions-in-phonology-at-130-pm-apr-7.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Interacting phonological processes are interesting for phonological theory because they often lead to opaque surface forms: forms where a process applied in an environment where it shouldn't have (overapplication) and forms where a process does not apply even though it looks like it should (underapplication). In my presentation I'll review …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Interacting phonological processes are interesting for phonological theory because they often lead to opaque surface forms: forms where a process applied in an environment where it shouldn't have (overapplication) and forms where a process does not apply even though it looks like it should (underapplication). In my presentation I'll review different ways people have talked about process interaction (rules, OT, Two-Level Phonology, automata) and then discuss some new ideas using logical transductions. Specifically, I discuss some possibilities for non-compositional process interaction.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="2023-Spring"></category></entry></feed>