<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>MLRG</title><link href="https://complab-stonybrook.github.io/mlrg/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://complab-stonybrook.github.io/mlrg/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://complab-stonybrook.github.io/mlrg/</id><updated>2024-10-24T10:04:54-04:00</updated><entry><title>Jeff on learning transducers (10/24)</title><link href="https://complab-stonybrook.github.io/mlrg/news/2024-fall/jeff-on-learning-transducers-1024.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2024-10-23T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2024-10-24T10:04:54-04:00</updated><author><name>Anton Hampe</name></author><id>tag:complab-stonybrook.github.io,2024-10-23:/mlrg/news/2024-fall/jeff-on-learning-transducers-1024.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The Discrete Infinity Argument is a central pillar of generative grammar. It posits that every natural language is an infinite set of finite structures. The argument rests on the observation that natural languages allow patterns such as (I know that you know that)+ John snores. I will contend that the …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The Discrete Infinity Argument is a central pillar of generative grammar. It posits that every natural language is an infinite set of finite structures. The argument rests on the observation that natural languages allow patterns such as (I know that you know that)+ John snores. I will contend that the discrete infinity argument&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;is an assumption rather than an empirical truth (problem of induction, cognitive finitism),&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;doesn’t establish the properties linguists want it to establish (in particular structural recursion),&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;has become empirically less viable as linguistic machinery has become more abstract over the years (e.g. nanosyntax).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This does not entail, however, that the general methodology built on top of the Discrete Infinity Argument is bunk. Generative grammar has arrived at the right conclusion for the wrong reason. I will present an alternative argument that does not need contentious assumptions such as the competence-performance distinction to motivate the generative methodology.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="2024-Fall"></category></entry><entry><title>Gödel's theorems: an incomplete journey (10/18)</title><link href="https://complab-stonybrook.github.io/mlrg/news/2024-fall/godels-theorems-an-incomplete-journey-1018.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2024-10-18T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2024-10-18T07:12:29-04:00</updated><author><name>Anton Hampe</name></author><id>tag:complab-stonybrook.github.io,2024-10-18:/mlrg/news/2024-fall/godels-theorems-an-incomplete-journey-1018.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Gary Mar and colleagues will present their project “A Year of Magical Thinking” that uses new media and AI to introduce students, as well as logicians, mathematicians, and linguists to the breadth and depth of Gödel’s Theorems. Gödel is widely regarded as the greatest logician of the 20th century …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Gary Mar and colleagues will present their project “A Year of Magical Thinking” that uses new media and AI to introduce students, as well as logicians, mathematicians, and linguists to the breadth and depth of Gödel’s Theorems. Gödel is widely regarded as the greatest logician of the 20th century and dreamed of establishing philosophical theses and ontological results with the rigour and precision of mathematics.  His dream was to a remarkable extent fulfilled. Despite their technical sophistication, Gödel’s logical theorems such as the Completeness Theorem [1930] and his Incompleteness Theorems [1931] have perennially managed to escape mere mathematics and shed light on larger philosophical issues. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A number of popular accounts of Gödel’s Incompleteness Theorems misrepresent the scope of Gödel’s ideas and their mathematical and philosophical significance. This workshop explores ways of presenting Gödel’s Incompleteness theorems using modal provability logics. Modal principles characterize properties of proof, time, and God reveal logical interconnections among Gödel’s theorems and philosophical conclusions about the unreality of time in the General Theory of Relativity [1949-1952] and in his Ontologischer Beweis [*1970], a modal ontological argument. Gödel’s success has often been attributed to his philosophy of mathematics, but his success is as much a tribute to his “mathematics of philosophy”, i.e., his ability to formulate philosophical problems in a manner that made them amenable to mathematical methods.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="2024-Fall"></category></entry><entry><title>Kenneth on agreement on multiple tiers (10/11)</title><link href="https://complab-stonybrook.github.io/mlrg/news/2024-fall/kenneth-on-agreement-on-multiple-tiers-1011.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2024-10-09T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2024-10-09T14:03:24-04:00</updated><author><name>Anton Hampe</name></author><id>tag:complab-stonybrook.github.io,2024-10-09:/mlrg/news/2024-fall/kenneth-on-agreement-on-multiple-tiers-1011.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This week &lt;a href="https://www.jeffreyheinz.net"&gt;Kenneth&lt;/a&gt; will be presenting his work on agreement on multiple tiers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Often, agreement targets the closest DP to some functional head which bears the right features.
But in some languages there are other hierarchies, such person/animacy, which outrank structural closeness.
Kenneth shows how such hierarchies can be …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This week &lt;a href="https://www.jeffreyheinz.net"&gt;Kenneth&lt;/a&gt; will be presenting his work on agreement on multiple tiers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Often, agreement targets the closest DP to some functional head which bears the right features.
But in some languages there are other hierarchies, such person/animacy, which outrank structural closeness.
Kenneth shows how such hierarchies can be implemented with a MTSL grammar over command strings.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="2024-Fall"></category></entry><entry><title>Sarah on generalizing BUFIA (10/04)</title><link href="https://complab-stonybrook.github.io/mlrg/news/2024-fall/sarah-on-generalizing-bufia-1004.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2024-10-04T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2024-10-04T01:13:26-04:00</updated><author><name>Anton Hampe</name></author><id>tag:complab-stonybrook.github.io,2024-10-04:/mlrg/news/2024-fall/sarah-on-generalizing-bufia-1004.html</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/heinz-jeffrey/bufia"&gt;BUFIA&lt;/a&gt;, the Bottom-Up Factor Inference Algorithm, is an algorithm for learning phonotactics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://paynesa.github.io/"&gt;Sarah&lt;/a&gt; will be presenting work on generalizing BUFIA to learn positive and negative grammars from unconventional string models.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="2024-Fall"></category></entry><entry><title>Thomas' reply to Chesi (09/27)</title><link href="https://complab-stonybrook.github.io/mlrg/news/2024-fall/thomas-reply-to-chesi-0927.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2024-09-24T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2024-10-09T13:59:16-04:00</updated><author><name>Anton Hampe</name></author><id>tag:complab-stonybrook.github.io,2024-09-24:/mlrg/news/2024-fall/thomas-reply-to-chesi-0927.html</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Thomas got his hands on a new paper by &lt;a href="https://www.nets.iusspavia.it/people/chesi.php"&gt;Chesi&lt;/a&gt; and he has some thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check the Google drive for the chance to have some thoughts on it too.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="2024-Fall"></category></entry><entry><title>Jeff on learning transducers (09/20)</title><link href="https://complab-stonybrook.github.io/mlrg/news/2024-fall/jeff-on-learning-transducers-0920.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2024-09-16T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2024-10-09T14:00:44-04:00</updated><author><name>Anton Hampe</name></author><id>tag:complab-stonybrook.github.io,2024-09-16:/mlrg/news/2024-fall/jeff-on-learning-transducers-0920.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This week &lt;a href="https://www.jeffreyheinz.net"&gt;Jeff&lt;/a&gt; will be presenting joint work with &lt;a href="https://remieyraud.github.io"&gt;Rémi Eyraud&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://dakotahlambert.com"&gt;Dakotah Lambert&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much of phonology is centered around studying maps from underlying representations to surface representations, in the form of OT grammars, phonological rules and other formalisms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Often these representation can be viewed as strings of symbols and …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This week &lt;a href="https://www.jeffreyheinz.net"&gt;Jeff&lt;/a&gt; will be presenting joint work with &lt;a href="https://remieyraud.github.io"&gt;Rémi Eyraud&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://dakotahlambert.com"&gt;Dakotah Lambert&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much of phonology is centered around studying maps from underlying representations to surface representations, in the form of OT grammars, phonological rules and other formalisms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Often these representation can be viewed as strings of symbols and in that case we can study these maps by looking at the finite state transducers (FSTs) that instantiate them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jeff will introduce us to a particular problem of learning string to string functions that are consistent with the structure of a deterministic FST, along with a sketch of a solution based on solving a system of string equations. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A conjecture regarding the nature of a sufficient sample will also be discussed.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="2024-Fall"></category></entry><entry><title>Anton on transducer continuity (09/13)</title><link href="https://complab-stonybrook.github.io/mlrg/news/2024-fall/anton-on-transducer-continuity-0913.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2024-09-10T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2024-09-11T02:08:52-04:00</updated><author><name>Anton Hampe</name></author><id>tag:complab-stonybrook.github.io,2024-09-10:/mlrg/news/2024-fall/anton-on-transducer-continuity-0913.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;There has been lots of work over the last ~20 years situating the phonotactics of natural language in certain classes of subregular languages and finding logical, automata-theoretic and algebraic characterizations of these classes. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has allowed linguists not only to better understand the cognitive nature of phonological generalizations but also …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;There has been lots of work over the last ~20 years situating the phonotactics of natural language in certain classes of subregular languages and finding logical, automata-theoretic and algebraic characterizations of these classes. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has allowed linguists not only to better understand the cognitive nature of phonological generalizations but also to design learning algorithms for them, something that is provably intractable if the regular space is not restricted in some way. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More recently there has been an increased effort to use similar methodology in the study of phonological processes. 
Ideally, the results linguists have uncovered while studying phonotactics would be transferable into this new domain, and indeed this has been possible in many cases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Continuous transductions allow us to lift certain classes of languages to classes of string-to-string functions in a way that has not been explored from a linguistic perspective yet. 
We will talk about what it means for a transduction to be continuous, how this notion relates to numerical continuous functions and more.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="2024-Fall"></category></entry><entry><title>M on compositional semantics (09/06)</title><link href="https://complab-stonybrook.github.io/mlrg/news/2024-fall/m-on-compositional-semantics-0906.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2024-09-02T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2024-09-02T12:33:06-04:00</updated><author><name>Anton Hampe</name></author><id>tag:complab-stonybrook.github.io,2024-09-02:/mlrg/news/2024-fall/m-on-compositional-semantics-0906.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This week M will be presenting original research on compositional semantics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although compositional semanticists tend to have a lot to say about the logical forms of lexical items and sentences, they tend to have a lot less to say about what truly makes their theory run: the nature of semantic …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This week M will be presenting original research on compositional semantics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although compositional semanticists tend to have a lot to say about the logical forms of lexical items and sentences, they tend to have a lot less to say about what truly makes their theory run: the nature of semantic rules.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal here is to investigate such rules, using the axiom "no semantic ambiguity" and the form of the interpretation relation's domain to reveal several interesting properties.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="2024-Fall"></category></entry></feed>